Walter Dundas Bathurst Papers, 1883-1923: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
Walter Dundas Bathurst Papers
1883-1923
C1588
Princeton University Library. Special Collections. Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
0.4 linear feet 1 box
Bathurst, Walter Dundas, 1859-1940
Consists primarily of three diaries that William Dundas Bathurst (1859-1940) kept while serving as an officer of the Association Internationale du Congo (AIC) from December 1883 to September 1886.
Walter Dundas Bathurst (1859-1940) was the son of Henry Thomas Dundas Bathurst (1811-1891), a career civil servant, and Margaret Ann Dundas Bathurst (1834-1916), of London. In 1883, he signed a contract with the Association Internationale du Congo (AIC) to serve for three years as an assistant at one of the association's stations.
Bathurst started his assignment in February 1884 at Vivi beyond Boma on the Congo River, where he came under the direct command of Welsh journalist and explorer H.M. Stanley. One of Bathurst's first tasks was to supervise road-building to link trading posts that had been established. In August 1884, Bathurst was posted to Kinshasa and worked alongside Arthur Swinburne, H.M. Stanley's former secretary. By the end of his term, Bathurst's role in Belgium's colonizing efforts had increased to a degree such that he was engaging in high-level negotiations with key players, including high-ranking representatives of the Teke people.
After his service with the AIC, Bathurst, with help from his father, continued in his father's footsteps as a civil servant with the Exchequer and Audit Department. He started out as a senior clerk auditing the accounts of the Gold Coast and Lagos in 1889. His service required his residency in Gibraltar for a time in the early 1890s.
Bathurst was married to Alice Matilda Willis (b. 1862) from 1891 until her death in 1917. They had one child, Marjorie Dundas Bathurst (b. 1892). In 1919, Bathurst married Rhona Batstone (1887-1977) with whom he had a son, Thomas Dundas Bathurst (1919-2006).
Principally, this collection consists of three diaries kept by Walter Dundas Bathurst (1859-1940) during his time as an officer with the Association Internationale du Congo (AIC) from December 1883 (with his departure from England) until September 1886. They offer a detailed, first-hand account of Bathurst's involvement in Belgium's colonization of the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Also included is some correspondence and ephemera related to Bathurst's time with the AIC as well as other professional correspondence and personal documents. Photographs, documents, and ephemera related to the Bathurst family are also included.
Open for research.
Purchase, 2017. (AM 2018-55)
No materials were removed from the collection during 2018 processing beyond routine appraisal practices.
Stanley, Henry M. (Henry Morton), 1841-1904—Sources; Great Britain. Exchequer and Audit Department--Sources.; International Association of the Congo—Sources.; Civil service—Great Britain--Sources.; Teke (African people)--Africa, Central--History--19th century--Sources.; Indigenous peoples--Africa, Central--History--19th century--Sources; Indigenous peoples--Congo (Democratic Republic)--History--19th century--Sources.; Belgium—Colonies—Congo (Democratic Republic).; Belgium--Colonies--Africa--Administration--Sources.; Congo (Democratic Republic)—Colonization--Sources.; Congo (Democratic Republic)—History—19th century--Sources.; Congo (Democratic Republic)—History—To 1908—Sources.; Congo (Democratic Republic)--Foreign relations--Belgium--Sources.; Great Britain—Politics and government—19th century--Sources.; Diaries -- 19th century.; Africa; European history
- Relating to Association Internationale du Congo Tenure, 1883-1890; 6 folders
  Includes Bathurst's diaries and correspondence.
  - Diaries, 1883 December 11-1886 September 24; 3 folders
    Each diary contains a list of outgoing letters entered on the upper inside cover.
    - Diary, 1883 December 11-1884 July 26; 1 folder (Folder 1)
      The second half of the notebook includes a partial script of James Albery's comedy, "The Two Roses," (1870) written in another hand.
    - Diary, 1884 July 27- 1886 February 28; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      The last couple of pages of the notebook includes a section entitled, "Curious Witch Palavers," in which three related stories are recounted.
    - Diary, 1886 March 1- September 24; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1884 September 4-1890; 3 folders
    - A.B. Swinburne, 1884 September 4; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      A memorandum signed by A.B. Swinburne from Leopoldville, sending supplies to Bathurst at Kinshasa.
    - Concerning Congo Star, 1890; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      Correspondence with both the British and Belgian authorities concerning Bathurst's application to be awarded the Congo Star.
      Incoming letters are in French.
  - Unused AIC Supply Request Form, circa 1885; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- General Correspondence, 1888-1895; 3 folders
  - John Rose Troup, 1889-1890; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    Four autograph letters by Bathurst's former colleague John Rose Troup, one of the few surviving veterans of the Rear Column of H.M. Stanley's Emin Pasha Relief Expedition, discussing the controversy that broke out about the expedition after their return to England.
  - Relating to Exchequer and Audit Department, 1888-1895; 1 folder (Folder 8)
    Correspondents include Henry Thomas Bathurst, C. Mallet, C.L. Ryan, and Richard A. Hoblyn, among others.
  - Henry Thomas Dundas Bathurst, 1891 September 13; 1 folder (Folder 9)
    Last letter Bathrust received from his father before his father's death.
- Personal Legal Documents, 1891-1923; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  Includes marriage and death certificates related to Bathurst's first wife, Alice Matilda, as well as a rental agreement.
- Receipt for Bathurst's Stay at a Hotel in Funchal, Madeira, 1886 November 12; 1 folder (Folder 11)
- Bathurst Family Documents, Photographs, and Ephemera, circa 1890; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  A couple of items relate to Henry Thomas Dundas Bathurst.
- 32101080851049 (Box B-001180)